Guide to the American Red Cross Vassar Relief Unit Records, 1914-1920
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
American Red Cross Vassar Relief Unit Records
1914-1920
American Red Cross. Vassar Unit
6 cubic feet (17 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Records concerning the Vassar Relief Unit's their work in France during and after World War I.
Administrative History
In January 1918, the Associate Alumnae of Vassar College voted to send a delegation of Vassar graduates to France to assist in the relief efforts of the American Red Cross. There are many sources of further information on the Vassar Relief Unit, including:
Lambie, Margaret. Verdun Experiences. Washington: Courant Press, 1945. [Main D570.9 .L28 1945]
Several articles in the Vasssar Quarterly [Main LH1.V3 V37]
The
Vassar College Subject Files
[folders 26.57-26.60]
Scope and Content Note
Records concerning the Vassar Relief Unit's their work in France during and after World War I, including letters, photographs, reports, financial statements, account books, clippings, circular letters, Red Cross publications, and Vassar Unit newsletters. Correspondence is primarily of Elsa Butler Grove and Margaret Lambie. There are also two diaries kept by Grove concerning a trip to France in 1914 and her experiences with the Vassar Unit in 1920. There are also various realia and uniforms of the Vassar Unit.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Elsa Butler Grove Papers
Subject Headings
Names:
Grove, Elsa Butler, 1884-1969; Lambie, Margaret; Townsend, Fanny P. Simpson, 1881-1970
Organizations:
Vassar College--Students
Subjects:
International relief; Medical social work--France--Verdun; World War, 1914-1918--France; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Red Cross; Women--Diaries; Women college students
Places:
France--Description and travel
Document Types:
Photographs; Account books; Diaries
VCL Categories
Vassar College Non-campus Organizations
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, July 2008.
Acquisition Information
Gift of multiple donors.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence
- Series II. Other Material
- Series III. Later Accession(A2005-005)
Container List
- SERIES I. Correspondence
  - 14 Jan 1918 to 26 Apr 1918 (Folder 1.1)
  - 29 Apr 1918 to 9 May 1918 (Folder 1.2)
  - 11 May 1918 to 5 June 1918 (Folder 1.3)
  - 7 June 1918 to 27 Sep 1918 (Folder 1.4)
  - 1 Febr 1921, 9-11 Oct1935, 21 Dec1958, 21 March 1972 and n.d. (Folder 1.5)
- SERIES II. Other Material
  - Bibliography of material pertaining to the Vassar Unit (Folder 1.6)
  - First members of the Vassar Unit (Folder 1.7)
  - French Tank (Folder 1.8)
  - Questionnaire for Biographical Address Register [Anabel Scharff Roberts, VC 1913] (Folder 1.9)
  - Required Equipment (Folder 1.10)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 1.11)
  - Articles (Folder 1.12-1.13)
  - Printed Material (Folder 1.14-1.17)
  - Clippings (Folder 1.18)
  - Photographs (Folder 2.19-2.20)
  - Scrapbooks (4) (Box 2)
  - Unprocessed material (Boxes 3-12)
- SERIES III. Later Accession (A2005-005)
  - Ambulance Plate, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Medals, ca. 1916-1920 (Box 1)
  - Machine Gun Cartridges, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Vassar Unit Rubber Stamps, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Shrapnel, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Rolled certificates, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, ca. 1917-1919 (Folder 2.1)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Folder 2.2)
  - "Verdun, 1920-1921 - 1936," Memoir of a return to Verdun by Elsa Butler Grove (Folder 2.3)
  - French Schools in War Time, 1917 (Folder 2.4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1917-1936 (Folder 2.5)
  - 2 copper and wood plaques entitled "Verdun et ses Champs de Bataille par le Capitaine d'Art, Gerard," (Box 3)
  - Publications, 1916-1919 (Box 3)
  - Red Cross Uniform of L. Little, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 4)
  - Uniform of Elsa Butler, ca. 1917-1919 (Box 5)